<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the unjust proceedings, in some matters of difference, between Mr. Williams Collins and Isaac Marlow; by several persons who pretend upon plain evidence, to acquit the one, and to give their judgement against the other.</title>
            <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M691B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832780</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1782:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the unjust proceedings, in some matters of difference, between Mr. Williams Collins and Isaac Marlow; by several persons who pretend upon plain evidence, to acquit the one, and to give their judgement against the other.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Isaac Marlow. London, July 2. 1697.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37254:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37254:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE Unjuſt Proceedings, IN Some Matters of Difference, BETWEEN Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Marlow;</hi> BY Several Perſons who pretend upon plain Evidence, to acquit the <hi>One,</hi> and to give their Judgment againſt the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere being a Written Paper brought by a Friend, and left with me for a ſhort time, wherein ſome Perſons had aſſumed the Liberty of paſſing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt me: And being other ways inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi> had printed two
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37254:2"/>or three ſingle Papers of the ſame Matter, relating in part to the ſame Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> and me, and that this Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Paper was deſign'd to be joyned to another Paper, which I believe to be the ſame I firſt mentioned; becauſe I have alſo heard, that that Paper was intended to be Printed; and having ſent to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> in my own Name, and other-ways endeavoured to get the ſight of one of his Papers, but cannot do it, it being pretended that they were not Corrected; and perceiving by the fewneſs of the Number aforeſaid that I hear are Printed, that they are not deſigned to be made very Publick, but rather to be Privately uſed to ſerve a preſent Intereſt; from which Clandeſtine Method of Proceeding, and the Reflections of the Written Paper, it being, as I am informed, read in the Preſence of too great a Number of Perſons to have the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof concealed, and ſince given forth to Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> I have no better way as I know of, to defend my Name and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from being wronged, than for Truth's ſake, leaſt that ſhould ſuffer with me, to give ſome Publick Notice of this Matter; to the End that if any Perſons have ought to ſay, for which they think I am blame-worthy, it may fairly ſtand the open Tryal of all Sober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in our Profeſſion, that will take the Pains to look into it, which is a more juſt Way, than to Rob me ſecretly of the Equity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of my Cauſe. And not knowing but this Paper may happen to come to the Sight of ſome Perſons, that are unacquainted with the firſt Occaſion of our Preſent Differences, I ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37254:2"/>briefly Premiſe ſome things for their better In formation.</p>
            <p>There having riſen ſome Perſons who firſt troubled the Baptized Churches with Challenges of Diſputes, Preaching and Printing for the common Way of Set-Form Singing, in the Publick Worſhip of God, I and others thought it our Duty, for the preſervation of the Peace of the Churches, on their Setled Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to improve our Talents, in defence of the Truth againſt that Humane Innovation, which through the Bleſſing of God we have done with good Succeſs, Clear Confutation, and the Publick Overthrow of their Cauſe, at laſt from the Confeſſions of their own Pens, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Unfair and Diſhoneſt Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Baſeneſs in particular againſt me, as may be ſeen in my Printed Books, referring to them: And I find the Spirit of Perſecution is ſtill endeavouring to draw a Cloud over my Publick Teſtimony againſt the Erroneous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Diſhoneſt Practices of my Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, as will appear in the following Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And to proceed, having conſidered the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Written Paper left with me, I returned by the ſame Hand to the Authors of it, a Paper ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying, That if they would ſend me that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Witneſſed, or Signed, or any other Paper of the ſame Nature, I would return them ſome brief Obſervations in Anſwer to it, in Order to prevent the Publick Miſchief of their Printing of it, which I thought might fall (not on me) but on themſelves and others: And having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged Matters with them, ſo as to prevent that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37254:3"/>Miſchief, unleſs they will act like Men caſting off all Common Prudence, as well as Juſtice and Equity, in our preſent Difference, I ſhall preſent the Reader with my Anſwer to a Paper they ſent me, Teſtimonially ſubſcribed unto by ſeveral Perſons, which Paper differs but little from the firſt, that contained all the Matter in their laſt Paper herein anſwered. And to the End my Paper ſent them in Anſwer to theirs may be the better diſtinguiſhed by the Reader, from what I have here added, I have cauſed it to be printed in a different Letter, as immediately follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Thing in that Paper which I ſhall here take Notice of, is, what I find therein concerning my Charging Mr. <hi>William Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> with a falſe Tranſlation of a piece of Latin, at the End of Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi>'s Breach Repaired, and with doing of it with a Deſign to decieve his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned Reader. To which they ſay, <hi>That to this Charge, the Matter appeared plainly before them, that the Tranſlation aforeſaid was alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the Preſs, from what it was in Mr.</hi> Collins <hi>his Copy, but without the Knowledge, Privity, or Conſent of Mr.</hi> Collins, <hi>and they acquit him of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Charge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which I briefly <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That they do not tell us who altered the Tranſlation they ſpeak of at the Preſs, nor on what Evidence they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37254:3"/>acquit Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> of it: Nay, altho' ſince I received their aforeſaid Paper, I ſent a Letter by ſeveral Brethren, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to let me know who was the Author of that falſe Tranſlation, (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to them) in Order to return my Anſwer to that particular; yet they, or thoſe of them that were then together, refuſed to tell us who was the Cauſe thereof, which gives me ground to ſuſpect, that they themſelves fear the plain Evidence they pretend to, cannot bear the Tryal of my Anſwer; and therefore I have reaſon ſtill to impute that falſe Tranſlation to Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> and none elſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> They tell us, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> cauſed a Letter to be immediately ſent to me by a Porter, who returned, and declared to Mr. <hi>William Collins,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> that he delivered it into my own Hand, and ſoon afterwards a Book, with the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion corrected, which they ſay I acknowledged I received.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The Corrected Book that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged I received, was only the ſame that I ſent my Brother, Mr. <hi>Luke Leader,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s for. And as to the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Porter, I never heard that ſuch a Porter could be produced; and I leave it to the Judgment of all impartial Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37254:4"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37254:4"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37254:5"/>whether there is any Reaſon to credit Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> and Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> in their own Cauſe, who are in an Evil Confederacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Sincere Teſtimony in my laſt Book to the contrary, till they have given Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Satisfaction for the Wrong they have done me and others in Print, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Dealings, which are ſo faſtned upon them, and plainly proved againſt them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in ſeveral Prints, that they have not been able to clear themſelves of the Guilt thereof; ſome of which things, relating to Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> are not ſo much as nam'd in my Accuſers Paper; ſo that their Attempt to clear Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> is but in part, and they fail of this, to their great Shame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They ſay, that Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> publiſhed this Expreſſion, <q>
                        <hi>That at the Aſſembly,</hi> to the beſt of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> had nothing to Anſwer for himſelf. And that in my laſt Book I publiſhed they affirm, that I ſaid, it's a contrived Lye of Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> ſo to charge me that I anſwered nothing for my ſelf. And they farther ſay, That upon Examination of this Matter, ſome of the Elders, who were preſent at the Aſſembly, do very well remember, that Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> anſwered nothing to the Charge of Mr. <hi>Collins.</hi> And whereas Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37254:5"/>expreſt himſelf modeſtly, that to the beſt of his Remembrance, Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> made no defence: From all which (ſay they) we conclude it's very injurious and unjuſt, for Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> to accuſe Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> of a contrived Lye, and we do juſtly acquit him of the ſame, a Lye being the Character of a Man of a very corrupt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and a Contrived Lye the worſt of that kind of Evil.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer 1.</hi> They do not tell us who thoſe Elders are, that they ſay do very well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that at the Aſſembly I anſwered nothing to the Charge of Mr. <hi>Collins;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may juſtly queſtion the Truth of what they ſay, conſidering that in my laſt Book there is the Publick Teſtimony of ſome of the moſt Honourable Elders in our Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and other Credible Witneſſes, who te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againſt Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s falſe accuſation of my being ſelf condemned, and who alſo ſay, that I did ſtrongly perſſiſt in my own Vindication in that Aſſembly.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> That poſitive Affirmation of theirs, that I ſaid it's a contrived Lye of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſo to charge me, that I anſwered nothing for myſelf is a baſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth, and ſuch a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Accuſation, as no Honeſt <hi>Heathen, Turk</hi> or <hi>Jew,</hi> in their right Senſes, would againſt the Light of Nature, dare to utter from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37254:6"/>the ſight of any of my Books, as they have done. For thoſe Words of Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> (at the End of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) That I had to the beſt of his Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance nothing to ſay in my own Defence, tho' they were teſtify'd againſt under the Hands of ſeveral Credible Witneſſes in my laſt Book, yet they were not at all charged by me, or any of my Witneſſes, on Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> as a Lye, or as any Evil, but in my laſt Book, Entituled, <hi>A Clear Confutation of Mr.</hi> Richard Allen, <hi>pag. 39.</hi> I have ſhewed (and its there confirmed by five<note n="*" place="margin">The five Witneſſes againſt Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> are, Mr. <hi>William Kif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin,</hi> Paſtour, Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Steed,</hi> Paſtour, Mr. <hi>John Scot,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour, Mr. <hi>Hugh Smith,</hi> Minister, and Mr. <hi>Luke Leader.</hi>
                     </note> Credible Witneſſes) that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Aſſertion, that I was ſelf-condemned at the Aſſembly, is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived Lye, which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal matter of Fact there charged and proved againſt Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> my unjuſt Judges have taken no Notice of at all in their Paper, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof they have in an evil Confederacy falſly accuſed me with another thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That I ſaid it's a Contrived Lye of Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> ſo to charge me, that I anſwered nothing for my ſelf: For which falſe and wicked Accuſation, thoſe Judges ought to manifeſt true Repentance, before either their Words or Writings will deſerve the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37254:6"/>leaſt Reputation among the Sons of Men.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> The Authours of the Paper I am here anſwering, (if it be true as they ſay) do clear me of the ſelf-condemnation, which Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> contrived a Lye to accuſe me with: For if it be true, that ſeveral Elders do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well remember, that at the Aſſembly I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered nothing to the Charge of Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> then it's evident, that I uttered nothing like ſelf condemnation; and if Silence be ſelf-condemning, we may equally affirm, that our Saviour condemned himſelf, (when he was ſilent before the High Prieſt, and ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Accuſation of thoſe falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that roſe up againſt him) which for any to ſay of Chriſt is Blaſphemy, <hi>Mark 14.57,</hi> to <hi>61,</hi> or <hi>62.</hi> So that thoſe Judges, in what they ſay to clear Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> of his Lye, have (I ſuppoſe it is unawares) cleared me of his falſe Accuſation, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Lye upon him, if what they ſay of the Elders be true.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iſaac Marlow.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having thus recited my Anſwer, which I ſent them on the <hi>3d.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1697. I ſhall here proceed (in order to take ſome farther Notice of ſeveral things in their Paper) to recite Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Paragraph in the laſt leaf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37254:7"/>of Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach repaired,</hi> wherein the falſe Tranſlation of the <hi>Latin</hi> is, and ſhall make ſome Breif Obſervations on it, and produce ſome new Evidence to faſten the falſe Tranſlation on Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> whoſe Paragraph immediately follows.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Author which Mr. <hi>M.</hi> cites out of <hi>Marlorate,</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. pretends it is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with what Words they praiſed God; that is, whether it was with the common Paſſover Hymn, or ſome other of Chriſt's own, which might be more ſuitable to the Occaſion; and whether they Sang this Praiſe, or Spake it Simply, the following words of the Author not being well render'd by Mr. <hi>Timme,</hi> I ſhall ſet down, they are theſe, <hi>Graecum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum laudem quidem, maxime quae Deo debetur, includit, non autem neceſſariò evincit, quòd ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinerint;</hi> i. e. The Greek Word indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes Praiſe, chiefly that which is due to God, but undoubtedly it doth evince that they Sang: I. From the Genuine Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Origininal Word. And, 2. From the Current of Learned Men, who go this Way.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Latin</hi> was falſly <hi>Engliſhed;</hi> for it ſhould be as it was Corrected by them, <hi>viz. But it doth not neceſſarily evince that they ſang,</hi> which is the ſame in ſeuce as my Author Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> reads it, <hi>viz. But it doth not thereupon follow that they did Sing it.</hi> Now as to the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that was made, (after this Abuſe was taken Notice of abroad) the whole Paragraph was not taken away, as it ought to have been, neither was the former part of it at all altered,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37254:7"/>which diſcovers the Deſign of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Unlearned Reader with the falſe Tranſlation of the <hi>Latin,</hi> as plainly appears from the Paragraph;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> findeth fault with Mr. <hi>Timme</hi>'s Tranſlation; for pretending it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether they ſang that Praiſe, or ſpake it ſimply, and then in Contradiction to him he aſſerts from the <hi>Latin,</hi> that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubtedly it doth evince that they ſang,</hi> which falſe Tranſlation agrees with Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s former Contradiction of Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> in the Paragraph.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe for Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to tell us, that Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> had not well rendred <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latin, when he had rendred his true Senſe, he muſt needs do it on purpoſe to deceive his Unlearned Reader with his falſe Tranſlation of it; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſeeing Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> had done it in the right Sence, there was no need at all for Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to write that Paragraph, or any thing elſe againſt him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis plain, that the Word [not] was left out on purpoſe to deceive his Unlearned Reader, becauſe there is no Reaſon to believe, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> did deſign poſitively to affirm from <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latin, that Chriſt and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples did not ſing the Hymn after Supper, or that he tranſlated the <hi>Latin</hi> to give an Undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Teſtimony to overthrow his own Cauſe, but that he made that falſe Tranſlation to make his Unlearned Reader believe, that undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly they did ſing, when he knew in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that the <hi>Latin</hi> leaves it undetermined, ſaying only, <hi>That it doth not neceſſarily evince</hi> (or ſhew) <hi>that they ſang,</hi> Mat. 26.30.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37254:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. It appears, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> wrote that Paragraph, on purpoſe to make that falſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, otherwiſe the Paragraph as afterwards corrected is a plain Contradiction to it ſelf: For he in the former part of it, that was never altered, as I hinted before, findeth fault with Mr. <hi>Timme</hi>'s Tranſlation, for pretending it is uncertain whether Chriſt and his Diſciples ſang, and then Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> tells us in his falſe Tranſlation, that they did undoubtedly or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſing; and he in the latter part of it, as Corrected, makes it uncertain whether they ſang or no, and ſo contradicts his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Words. And therefore ſeeing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, as Corrected, is not Sence, but a plain Contradiction of it ſelf, and that the Falſe Tranſlation of the <hi>Latin</hi> renders the Paragraph true Engliſh, Coherent, Agreeing, and good Sence, and that there is no reaſon to think Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> did write the former part againſt Mr. <hi>Timme</hi>'s Tranſlation, to confirm its true Sence, as Corrected afterwards in the ſame Paragraph, but that he wrote it as uncorrected, to oppoſe our Author's Evidence of the Simple Signification of the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Hymneo,</hi> to Praiſe: It muſt then follow, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> could have no other End in writing againſt Mr. <hi>Timme</hi>'s true Sence, but to deceive his Unlearned Reader. And ſeeing Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> both in Converſe and Print, has ſo own'd himſelf as the Author of that Paragraph, that he cannot impute the Writing of it to any other Perſon, he cannot any ways clear himſelf of that falſe Tranſlation of the Latin.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37254:8"/>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> appears to be Author of that Falſe Tranſlation, from the Account the Printer has given of it to clear himſelf to two or three Credible Witneſſes, who have lately given me their Teſtimony in writing, ſigned with their own Hands, that when they asked the Printer, who made the <hi>Engliſh</hi> contrary to Mr. <hi>Timme's</hi> Tranſlation of <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latin, he ſaid, that he did think, that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> had ſaid ſome time ſince, as if they two had done it by Agreement; but, ſaid he, I know not of any thing more, then that I agreed to Print it as he ordered it, for we do not uſe to alter Copies, except it be to rectifie the Words, and make them good Engliſh, if they are not ſo, but to print them according to the Mind of the Author. And the Printer's Son told them to this Effect, that he did not Correct it, nor Compoſe it, as he remembred, but he was Confident of this, that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> finding as he thought, that the Engliſh put down by Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> did not ſuit his Deſign, altered it himſelf, and ſaid, he did not doubt but Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> would own it, becauſe he did acknowledge it in a Paper he had lately printed at their Houſe, wherein to clear Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> he took it upon himſelf, and he did not remember above two of them Papers printed.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what the Printers have ſaid: My Obſervations follow:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That altho' the Printer thinks, that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> had ſaid, as if they two had dore the falſe Tranſlation contrary to <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s Latin, laying the Fault on the Printer as well as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37254:9"/>on himſelf, yet we ſee how the Printer clears himſelf from printing it otherways than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Order. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the falſe Tranſlation is imputed as it ſeems in Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Paper to him alone. Now ſeeing I cannot obtain the ſight of his Paper, I have reaſon to believe that he ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects it to be ſo ſlight a thing, as that it cannot bear the Tryal of my Anſwer, or that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> has ſo worded the Contents thereof, as that he can play faſt and looſe with the Matter to help Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> and himſelf too, when and where he pleaſeth it ſhould ſerve either Intereſt. However, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> has conceal'd the ſight of his Paper from me, notwithſtanding (after I was ſatisfied they were printed) I ſent a Friend with a Letter under my Hand on purpoſe to himſelf for it: And conſidering that I alſo ſent ſome Friends with a Letter of Requeſt, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, under my own Hand, to know of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Judges, who was the Author of the falſe Tranſlation, and they alſo refuſed to tell me who the Author of it was, to their Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, I have therefore no reaſon to impute that wilful Abuſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the falſe Tranſlation, to any other than Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> who (except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what pertains to that) has own'd that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph in Print, and otherways as the Author of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It appears that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> was the Author of that falſe Tranſlation, for it is not rational to believe, that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> without the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> would dare to make ſo great an Alteration in the Tranſlation, as to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37254:9"/>put the Word <hi>[undoubtedly]</hi> into the Engliſh, when he might have ſerved his Deſign with only leaving out the Word <hi>[not]</hi> and have excuſed it with the Pretence of an accidental Blot in the Copy, that covered it from the Printer, or otherways concealed his Fault from Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> without hazarding the Favour of his Friendſhip, by abuſing his Tranſlation with putting in the Word undoubtedly (inſtead of the right Words) which ſhews not only that the Faiſe Tranſlation was made on purpoſe to deceive, but alſo that it is not likely Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> with ſo great an Alteration, aſſerting the Current of Learned Men for it, made that falſe Tranſlation without the Agreement of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> to it, or rather, if they did it by Agreement, then (from what hath been proved from the former part of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Paragraph) 'tis plain that their Agreement was only Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Conſent and Approbation of the falſe Tranſlation, which Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> had made and contrived to deceive his Unlearned Reader with, among whom thoſe Books were likely moſt to be diſperſed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It appears, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> had a Deſign in Writing that Paper, wherein the falſe Tranſlation is, to abuſe ſome of my Authors, or knew that he had done it from the Title that is on his Paper, <hi>viz. Some Reflections on Mr.</hi> Marlow<hi>'s undue Citations of ſeveral Learned Men:</hi> For, conſidering that neither Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> nor any others, have been ever able to ſhew that I have falſly cited any one Author, or to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that I have added to them any more than their due; it is therefore evident from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37254:10"/>the Title Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> has given, or Conſented to, by ſuffering it to remain on that Paper, that he deſigned to abuſe ſome of my Authors, or knew that he had done it, under Pretence that I had not duely cited them; otherwiſe he would have thought the Title to be a wrong Title, and ſhould not have let it paſs into the the World.</p>
            <p n="8">8. It appears, that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that falſe Tranſlation, from the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a Letter I have now by me, Written and Signed with Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Name, by his own Hand, which Letter is in my <hi>Narrative of the Riſe, Occaſion, and Management of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie of Singing:</hi> Printed about five years agoe, at the End of my <hi>Reply</hi> to Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach Repaired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, in a Letter I ſent Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> which is alſo Printed in the aforeſaid Narrative, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt Mr. <hi>William Collins,</hi> for dealing ſo diſingenuouſly with me, at the End of Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Book, and I only there mentioned in particular his Dealing ſo unfairly by my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor Mr. <hi>Timme,</hi> (the very Caſe in hand of the falſe Tranſlation) to which Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> in his Letter return'd me this Anſwer, in theſe Words, <hi>viz. Brother</hi> Marlow, <hi>I have received yours of the</hi> 20th. <hi>of this Month, and in Anſwer thereunto, I reply to your Exception againſt Mr.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Collins: <hi>That which is contained in that wrote by him, is not matter of difference between you and I, therefore that I am not concerned with in chooſing him and the Reſt;</hi> viz. that he chooſe to meet together with others choſen by me, to inſpect into Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Abuſes in his Book, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37254:10"/>I had before complained of. Now ſeeing Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s unfair Dealing with Mr. <hi>Timme,</hi> which was about the Falſe Tranſlation, is ſaid by Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> (in anſwer to that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) not to be matter of Difference between him and me; and that he alſo tells us, he is not concerned with that contained in that wrote by Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> viz with that unfair Dealing with Mr. <hi>Timme</hi> and <hi>Marlorate</hi>'s La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin in Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Paper, 'tis very plain that Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> has there cleared himſelf of the falſe Tranſlation, and fixed it on Mr. <hi>William Collins,</hi> as the Author of it.</p>
            <p>In the next place, as to the Correction which is talked ſo much of in Defence of Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> and that he ſent a Letter by a Porter to me, I have this to ſay, that before I had read Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s <hi>Breach repaired</hi> quite through, I firſt heard of the falſe Tranſlation, neither from Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> nor from Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> but from the Noiſe that was ſpread abroad of it by others; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had ſeen it corrected in any Book, my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mr. <hi>Luke Leader,</hi> brought me the Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Writing, from a Book Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and my Brother wrote it with his own Hand, and it ſtill remains in my Uncorrected Book, (which to my beſt remembrance Mr. <hi>Keach</hi> gave me) and after this I deſired my Brother to bring me a corrected Book from Mr. <hi>Keach,</hi> who took down ſeveral of thoſe Boks from off his Shelf, before he could find one of them corrected, which was the firſt I ſaw of them, and I believe I never ſaw above one more Corrected. Moreover, ſome time after they were pretended to be corrected, I enquired for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37254:11"/>one of thoſe Books at Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Bookſellers, and at another place where they were to be ſold, the one offered me one of thoſe Books un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrected, and the other told me he had none ſo altered, and that he knew nothing of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, no longer ago than in the Months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> 1696. 'tis teſtified to me, and I can ſhew it, that two of thoſe Books were bought at Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s, or of his Daughters, that ſold them in their Shop, both of which are uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
            <p>So that I believe the Correction was made but of a very few, only at firſt to blind my Eyes, that I ſhould not give any Publick Notice of that Abuſe. And as to the Letter they ſay was brought me by a Porter, about the Correction of that falſe Tranſlation, I ſhall further An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as I did before in my laſt Book, Entituled, <hi>A Clear Confutation of Mr.</hi> Richard Allen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 37. That I have not the leaſt knowledge of any ſuch Letter that was ſent me, or came to my Hands from Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, concerning that Matter, (and I here add) or that I ever heard the leaſt mention of any ſuch Letter or Porter, till laſt Summer, after Dr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s <hi>Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on Mr.</hi> Allen<hi>'s Eſſay</hi> was Publiſhed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he took Notice of Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s falſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, which was about five years after it was pretended that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſent that Letter: But if he had ſent me an hundred Letters, to ſignifie his Correction, they could not clear him of his firſt deſign, to abuſe his Unlearned Reader with his falſe Tranſlation of the Latin.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37254:11"/>
            <p>Moreover, my falſe Accnſers in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Paper ſay, That <hi>Having ſeen a Book lately Printed and Publiſhed by Mr.</hi> Iſaac Marlow, — <hi>Wherein there are very ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and falſe Reflections upon him,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Collins) <hi>the Elder of the Church, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him unworthy to be a Member with them, much more their Paſtour; and whereas there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in a Church-way againſt the ſaid Mr.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>he being at preſent no Member in any of the Baptized Churches in and about this City, or elſewhere, We hold it our Duty — to put the Matter of Fact, as it appears upon Evidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, with our Opinion of it, in Writing, that our Reverend Brother</hi> (<hi>viz. Mr.</hi> William Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins) <hi>may make uſe of it for the clearing of his Innocency, as he ſhall ſee cauſe; and that we may bear our Teſtimony againſt the Proceedings of Mr.</hi> Marlow, <hi>as ſcandalous, and tending to the Diſturbance of the Peace of Churches, and that all Perſons that are in our Communion may mark him as ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. We may plainly ſee what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries my falſe Accuſers are to common Juſtice and Equity, when it pinches one of their Singing-Party, for they count it a Diſturbance to the Peace of Churches, for me to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Publick Wrong committed by Mr. <hi>Collins;</hi> and they are ſo averſe to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Jeſus Chriſt in his Church, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' before they ſent me their Paper herein anſwered, in a Paper I ſent to them in Anſwer to their Minds, by two Meſſengers, that I ſhould bring the matter of Difference between Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> and me to a hearing before them, I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37254:12"/>gave them my Opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſeeing they concerned themſelves, that the matter of Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference ſhould not lye as it did, Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Church, whoſe proper buſineſs it is, ſhould be rather moved to look into it, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, they would not deſiſt from their Arbitrary Proceedings againſt me. Nor have they given me the leaſt Anſwer to another Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per I ſent them on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>24th.</hi> 1697. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſignified, that I heard they had given forth their Paper to Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> and that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Satisfaction from them for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve, how they are for ſetting their Mark upon me, ſo Publickly, that all Perſons in their Communion may take Notice of me, as ſuch as they repreſent me to be; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Charge of a contrived Lye is confirmed againſt Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> in my laſt Book, by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of ſuch Worthy and Credible Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes as Mr. <hi>William Kiffin,</hi> Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Steed,</hi> Paſtor, Mr. <hi>John Scot,</hi> Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Hugh Smith,</hi> Miniſter, and Mr. <hi>Luke Leader;</hi> and conſidering that the farther matter of Fact in difference between him and me is publiſhed in Print, I hope our People know me ſo well, as to diſtinguiſh me by my true Marks from Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> and his Confederates: And ſurely their Time had been better ſpent in humbling themſelves for their Iniquities, and in wipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the black Mark of their Paper from off themſelves by true Repentance, inſtead of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it forth, as I heard they did, to Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> ſince I ſent them my before-recited An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37254:12"/>
            <p n="3">3. I deſire it may be noted, what a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit is like to follow me, if I ſhould joyn my ſelf to any Church, and how trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome my Adverſaries would be to the Peace and Union of any People that ſhould receive me into Communion; ſeeing they would ſeek their Remedy, as they call it, or rather their Revenge againſt me by them: For 'tis ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to expect no better Dealing from them, than their falſe Teſtimony already given, or inſtead of that falſe Accuſation in their Paper, ſome other piece of Forgery, that would paſs a Church eaſier with their preſſing Influence, to ſway the People to a wrong Judgment againſt me, to blemiſh my Teſtimony for Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: And had thoſe Singers power ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Wills, I believe I ſhould quickly feel the Smart of it, for my Faithfulneſs to the pure Intereſt of the Baptized Churches, and for Reproving them for their Iniquity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to what they ſay in their Paper of my being at preſent no Member in any of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Churches, I ſhall farther Anſwer, That I believe they cannot but know, that I was lately a Member of a Baptized Church here in <hi>London,</hi> and that they, or ſome of them, have ſeen my Printed Caſe of <hi>Separation</hi> from it, which was never yet anſwered, nor the Truth thereof, as I know of, at all denyed by the Church, or any Member of it. And were there any particular matter concerning my Proceedings, for which I could be juſtly bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, I believe I ſhould, e're now, have heard enough of it in Print; but the Lord has ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected my Steps, as to ſhut the Mouths of all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37254:13"/>Men in Publick, whatever private Inſinuations they uſe againſt me. And tho' I am not again joyned to any People, it is not becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find in this City a Baptized Church in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Order, that as a Church, I could have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with at the Lords Table, if it were not for the Corruption of ſome Singing-members in their Fellowſhip, who bar my Conſcience from their Communion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As to what my Unjuſt Judges alſo ſay in their Paper, that my Reflections on Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> in my Book lately Publiſhed, render him unworthy to be a Member of the Church, much more their Paſtor, I ſhall only return this Anſwer, that ſeeing my Reflections are ſo juſt and true, that neither he nor his Friends are able to clear him of any one of them; it then follows from the Judgment of his own Friends, and my Adverſaries, that he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be either a Paſtor or Member of the Church; and I beleive ſo too, while he is under his preſent Circumſtances of Sin. And I likewiſe believe the ſame of his Fellow-Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Authors of the aforeſaid Paper, who are alſo unworthy of Church-Communion, 'till they have manifeſted true Repentance for their unjuſt Judgment, falſe Accuſation, and Forged Lye againſt me deceitfully, to cover Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi>'s Lye: And whoever reads the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Singing from firſt to laſt, they may plainly ſee that with the Bringing among our Churches the falſe Worſhip of Common Set-form Singing, there has appeared in it's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſuch a Diſhoneſt Spirit of Deceit and Lying, as ought to be abhorred, and count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37254:13"/>unworthy of the Society of all ſober Men, and is a plain Mark of an apoſtatizing Spirit from true Religion, <hi>A Lye being</hi> (as my falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers ſay in their Paper) <hi>the Character of a Man of a very corrupt Conſcience, and a Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Lye the worſt of that kind of Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, I have ſhewed in my laſt Book, (called <hi>A Clear Confutation,</hi> &amp;c.) not only how Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> has abuſed the Tranſlation of the Latin of <hi>Auguſtine Marlorate,</hi> who was a Reformed Miniſter, and Faithful Martyr of Jeſus Chriſt, but alſo how he has abuſed the Learned and Worthy Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> who in his Annotations and Tranſlation of the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> has eight ſeveral times given the Signification of the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Hymnos,</hi> to be Simply Praiſe, and in no one place as I can find, has tranſlated it a Song of Praiſe, and yet Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> in his aforeſaid printed Paper, has the Confidence to ſay, that Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Pſalm</hi> the <hi>3d. Intends nothing leſs than a Song of Praiſe;</hi> tho' Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> has there ſaid no more on the Signification of the Word, <hi>Hymnos,</hi> than <hi>Tehilla,</hi> in Gr. <hi>Hymnos, a Hymn</hi> or <hi>Praiſe.</hi> Beſides, Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> in the ſame Paper, at the End of Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Breach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, in Anſwer to me on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78.63. has cited <hi>Jun.</hi> and <hi>Trem.</hi> thus, <hi>Non Epithalamio celebratae ſunt,</hi> i. e. were not Honoured with a Wedding-Song: But this is a Wrong to thoſe Authors, for <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> in their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Bible tranſlates the Text thus, <hi>Juvenes ejus abſumeret ignis, &amp; Virgines ejus non lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur;</hi> that is, <hi>The fire conſumed his Young Men, and his Virgins were not Praiſed:</hi> So that conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37254:14"/>how apt Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> is to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent and abuſe Authors,<note place="margin">See my Clear Confutation, P. <hi>7, 8, 43.</hi>
               </note> and his wronging the firſt Baptized Churches, contrary to their Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Confeſſion of Faith; which teſtifies againſt his Publick Slander of them, and his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s Cheat, about the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Rhime and Metre, and his contrived Lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, which is juſtly ſo termed, from his Deſign to deceive with it, and from his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate doing of it, by Writing his Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Deceit, and giving of it forth to Print: I think therefore we have no Reaſon to Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit his Words or Writings, 'till he has mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted Sincere Repentance for thoſe Evils.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I have alſo ſhewed in my laſt Book, (Entituled, <hi>A Clear Confutation of Mr.</hi> Richard Allen, <hi>and his five Commendators, from their own Confeſſions</hi>) what a Pernicious Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Error Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions have broached in Print among our Churches; <hi>viz. That Chriſtian Churches have liberty to Order ſuch Accidental Modes and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Divine Worſhip, as are not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly preſcribed in the Word, as they ſhall judge moſt for Edification:</hi> Which ſtrikes at a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Principle, and tends to the Ruine of ours, and the Proteſtants Reformation more in General; it being, as I have proved in my aforeſaid Confutation, oppoſite to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our firſt Reformers from Popery, and is contrary to the <hi>Preſbiterians, Independants,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts</hi> Confeſſions of Faith, <hi>Article</hi> 1. and <hi>Art.</hi> 21, 22. To which laſt is Mr. <hi>William Collins</hi>'s Name: So that he is Apoſtatizing in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37254:14"/>Spirit, from a Foundation-Principle of the Proteſtant Reformation: And let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge from what I have ſaid, whether it be not from Moral Honeſty too.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add, That as I never had any Difference with Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> in any other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters than of Religion; ſo my Conſcience bears me Witneſs, that I have not thus diſcovered his Iniquity, from any Prejudice againſt him, but that the Truth he has endeavoured to ſtifle by his Deceit, may be made manifeſt; and to diſcourage him and his Confederates, (and others hereafter) from defending their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors by ſuch Foul and Miſchievous Ways, which if they were not laid open, and made Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, to deter others, no ſober Chriſtian would be able to appear publickly for the Truth he profeſſeth, tho' it be never ſo violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſaulted, without the hazard of his Honeſt Reputation, his being tyred with the Increaſe of Charge in printing, and of ſuch a Labyrinth of Difficulties, as but few are able to paſs through; which I hope the Lord in his due time will deliver me from, and diſcover to our Churches, and make them ſenſible of the baſe Confederacy of my Adverſaries, and their Treachery, againſt the Baptized Intereſt in this Nation, more and more.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iſaac Marlow.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 2. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37254:15"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bar ye are Forgers of Lyes, ye are all Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of no Value, <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 13.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>The Proud have forged a Lye againſt me, <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 119.69.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Deliver my Soul, O Lord, from Lying Lips, and from a Deceitful Tongue, <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 120.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>I hate and abhor Lying, but thy Law do I love, <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 119.163.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Lye non one to another, <bibl>
                     <hi>Col. 3.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe Witneſs againſt thy Neighbour, <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 20.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>A falſe Witneſs that ſpeaketh Lyes God hateth, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 6.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>A falſe Witneſs ſhall not be unpuniſhed, and he that ſpeaketh Lyes ſhall not eſcape, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 19.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>The Mouth of them that ſpeak Lyes ſhall be ſtopped, <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 63.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thine Heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin upon him, <bibl>
                     <hi>Lev. 19.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Ye ſhall do not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs in Judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect the Perſon of the Poor, nor honour the Perſon of the Mighty, <bibl>
                     <hi>Lev. 19.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Now we command you Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the Tradition which be received of us, <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Theſ. 3.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>He that covereth his ſins, ſhall not proſper; but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall have Mercy, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
